I've never heard of a mechanism
described in a study looking at people's
mitochondria and the impact that
consumed nitrates have you see when we
consume nitrates they're converted to
nitrites in your mouth by your oral
bacteria or they can be absorbed through
salivary circulation if converted to
nitrites these nitrites are
spontaneously converted to nitric oxide
in the stomach acid to then be absorbed
later on into the bloodstream thereby
vasodilating our blood vessels
essentially opening them reducing blood
pressure but that's not why we're here
to discuss nitric oxide specifically
we're interested in what happens inside
your cells in these organel called
mitochondria mitochondria serve many
crucial functions some of which we've
discussed on physionic before but we're
going to focus on the trusty Powerhouse
of the cell where mitochondria generate
large amounts of cellular energy in the
form of ATP so that's adenosine
triphosphate so for now just know that
nitrate consumption can increase nitric
oxide production which as we'll see has
a unique effect on mitochondria the
study that we're opening up is this one
in this randomized control trial
participants consumed sodium nitrate or
they consumed a placebo so sodium
chloride participants consumed either
intervention so nitrate or Placebo for 3
days and then they had muscle biopsies
taken to access mitochondria Rich tissue
they then underwent a Six-Day wash out
period meaning they no longer consume
the intervention for 6 days to clear
their system and then they switch to the
other condition That's a classic
crossover design that theoretically
controls for genetic differences and
diet differences now if we look at the
nitrate and nitrate levels in the blood
we see that when people were consuming
nitrates they did experience an increase
in blood values of both nitrate and
nitrites the Assumption then is that
nitric oxide levels are greater as well
this is a nice to see because sometimes
assumptions make asses out of you and me
here we're confirming intervention
actually provides what it's supposed to
do okay that's the Baseline info but now
what happened to their mitochondria well
one of several data is that mitochondria
are able to produce more ATP in the same
time frame remember ATP adenosine
triphosphate is the main energy currency
within our cells in fact mitochondria
now generate
23% more ATP that's a pretty sizable
jump from one molecule nitrates but the
fun doesn't stop there because the
researchers assessed mitochondrial po
ratio more simply explained they
measured a measure of mitochondrial
efficiency at generating cellular energy
called oxidative phosphorilation
efficiency or po ratio here's those data
notice again black is the nitrate
condition there is an improvement higher
is better in mitochondrial efficiency so
what is going on here how are nitrates
leading to these changes in
mitochondrial function and what else
changes in mitochondria let's address
the second question first do other
aspects of mitochondria change for
example is mitochondrial biogenesis
affected mitochondrial biogenesis if
you're not familiar is the generation of
more mitochondria which occurs by
mitochondria pinching together and
splitting in two now there are a variety
of key proteins involved in that process
like pgc1 Alpha and tfam so if we look
at the gene expression of these key
biogenesis proteins the one line cutting
across is the standard so Placebo and
the individual dots are the results of
each individual experiment some go way
up and some go down the net effect is a
nonsignificant effect denoted by the NS
up top this was further confirmed
looking at mitochondrial DNA both data
sets did not budge although you could
argue that some people experienced
substantial upregulation of some of
these biogenesis genes the average
result is no effect of nitrates
indicating no mitochondrial biogenesis
so this leads us back to how nitrates
are then improving mitochondrial
efficiency in ATP production rate well
for us to understand that we need to
understand a few more in-depth things
about how mitochondria work if you're
not here to understand that you're
welcome to leave the takeaway here is so
far that nitrates improve mitochondrial
efficiency all right now for those of
you interested in the details there's
also of some data on how nitrates affect
V2 a metric of oxygen consumption and a
critical metric for performance and
health there's some counterintuitive
effects of nitrates on V2 along with
some other details on nitrate
consumption that I'll be covering in the
extended version of this video that
we're in it's all part of the physionic
Insiders if you're so inclined to have
unfiltered access to this full video
plus all my other videos written
summaries Insider podcasts and more the
link to join the insiders is in the
description okay one explanation for
this nitric oxide effect is defined in
other research that the researchers
reference apparently nitric oxide
reduces mitochondrial respiration what
does that mean well if we zoom into your
mitochondria there are a complex of
proteins five of them called the
electron transport chain although
technically only four engage with
electrons these electrons which come
from food after considerable biochemical
Al alterations are pushed from complex
one to complex 4 in so doing these
complexes pump protons out of the inner
section of the mitochondria thereby
creating a gradient where the protons
are in Greater number in this inter
membrane space between the two membrane
mitochondria has then the innermost area
of the mitochondria this is critical
because it creates a proton motive Force
which means that the protons move down
their concentration gradient to go back
to the inner section of the mitochondria
now in so doing this motive Force turns
the fifth complex the ATP synthes into
producing new ATP molecules from spent
ADP molecules this is the major way by
which we produce cellular energy
ATP well look here at complex 4 there's
an interaction of oxygen molecules that
helps this process along however it so
happens that nitric oxide like that
produced from nitrates also binds the
same region out competing oxygen
molecules as such the exchange of
electrons is slowed between the
complexes of the electron transport
chain so why would that be a good thing
well getting in the way of a normal
process well the slowing of electron
exchange is apparently a way to
stabilize the electron so fewer El El
Rons will slip off the chain and create
free radicals damaging molecules that
can be formed so although the
researchers don't show evidence of
reduced free radicals the idea is that
nitric oxide allows each electron to
fulfill its purpose instead of flying
off the electron transport chain and
forming a free radical like a reactive
oxygen species in addition because
electrons fulfill their function by
allowing protons to be pumped out the
proton motive force is more intact
allowing more ATP generation for the
same level of electron input it's a bit
complicated but really cool once you
wrap your head around it nonetheless
don't you think anyway there's something
else that happens in mitochondria due to
nitrate consumption there's a critical
protein embedded in the inner membrane
the uh same membrane that contains the
electron transport chain proteins that
we discussed just now the primary
function of protein which is called the
Adine nucleotide translocase orent is to
allow ADP and ATP to exchange from the
inside of the mitochondrian back out to
the rest of the cell as well as Supply
the mitochondrian with ADP to turn into
ATP through the ATP synthes that we
discussed earlier the complex 5 it is
highly impermeable to other molecules
meaning it is highly selective in only
allowing the exchange of these two
molecules but funny enough It Isn't So
impermeable that it doesn't allow
protons through that means the protons
that the electron transport chain are
pumping out of the inner area of the
mitochondrian can literally leak back
into the intersection of the
mitochondria this proton leak means
there's reduced mitochondrial efficiency
since we're seeing increased
mitochondrial efficiency with nitrate
consumption
how are nitrates affecting this process
let's pop open one more data notice this
is a measure of ant the same protein the
higher the individual dots go the
greater ant protein levels remember
these dots are linked by a line because
they represent the placebo measurement
and nitrate measurement of the same
person the average effect of nitrate
consumption is a reduction in ENT this
is believed to be yet another way that
nitrates increase mitochondrial
efficiency reducing proton leak and
keeping protons where they should be in
the intermembrane space of the
mitochondria now that's a lot of
information so what are the big
takeaways here well real quick I'd be
remiss not to mention that this study
was in young healthy men and while I do
speculate that this applies to women as
well I'd be less confident it happens
with people with certain chronic
illnesses although it might that
disclaimer said these data show clearly
that consuming nitrates like those found
in spinach beets celery and even salami
smoked fish and many other sources
contributes to improving mitochondrial
efficiency it should be noted that the
study was using isolated nitrates not
derived from food so we can only speak
to the actual impact of nitrates alone
overall if mitochondrial efficiency is
important to you nitrates might be the
answer otherwise I would highly
recommend checking out this next video
[Music]